Guide to the Walter Hinds Allen Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Walter Hinds Allen papers
1894-2016
1894-1920
MS 2056
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.42
(4 boxes)
The papers document the wartime activities and family background of Walter Hinds Allen. The bulk of the papers consist of correspondence with Allen's family, especially his parents, Walter and Grace. Much of this correspondence was written during and in the years immediately after the Spanish-American War. Other materials in the papers include photographs of Allen, his family, and his classmates, as well as biographical writings and genealogical charts of the Allen and related families. Materials date from 1869 to 2016, with the bulk of the materials from 1894 to 1920.
Allen, Walter Hinds, 1875-1938
Arrangement
Arranged into three series: I. Correspondence, 1894-1901. II. Photographs, 1895-1896. III. Biographical and genealogical materials, 1895-2016.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alice Wiltrout Moffa, 2016.
Biographical / Historical
Walter Hinds Allen was born on January 9, 1875 in Newton Highlands, Massachusetts to Walter Allen, a journalist. He attended Yale College (1895) and the Sheffield Scientific School (1896). Allen also worked on a Ph.D in Mathematics at the Yale Graduate School from 1895 to 1898, but he left school to participate in the Spanish-American War. He served with the Connecticut Naval Militia from 1896 to 1898 and from 1902 to 1903. He also served in the United States Navy from June to September of 1898. He continued his career in the Navy when he was commissioned as a Civil Engineer with the rank of Lieutenant in 1906 and eventually achieved the rank of Captain. For much of his career, he worked as a public works officer in which he led engineering projects at various naval bases and yards, including the Philadelphia Naval Yard, in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, the Brooklyn Naval Yard, in Brooklyn, New York, and the Twelfth Naval District in San Francisco, California. He also participated in the building of the Montauk Point, Bay Shore, and Rockaway, Long Island aviation stations, all located in New York. He died in San Francisco, California on April 19, 1938.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the wartime activities and family background of Walter Hinds Allen. The bulk of the papers consist of correspondence with Allen's family, especially his parents, Walter and Grace. Much of this correspondence was written during and in the years immediately after the Spanish-American War. Other materials in the papers include photographs of Allen, his family, and his classmates, as well as biographical writings and genealogical charts of the Allen and related families. Materials date from 1869 to 2016, with the bulk of the materials from 1894 to 1920.
Spanish-American War, 1898; Allen, Walter Hinds, 1875-1938; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School. Class of 1896; Yale College (1887- )
- Correspondence, 1894-1901; Series I (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series comprises correspondence sent by Walter Hinds Allen to his family, especially his parents, Walter Allen and Grace Allen. This includes correspondence written from Louisiana, Texas, and Mexico during his Naval service in the Spanish-American War, 1898.
- Photographs, 1895-1896; Series II
  This series comprises photographs of Walter Hinds Allen, his family, and his classmates. Also included are a few photographs of Walter Hinds Allen's and Edith Allen's graves at Arlington National Cemetery. While almost all of the photographs are identified as being related to Allen, some of the photographs have no description.
  Series II is arranged alphabetically.
  - Allen with classmates, Circa 1895-circa 1896 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Printouts of family members' graves and a family portrait of the Allens, Circa 1910-circa 1919, circa 2000-circa 2010 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified group photograph, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Photograph depicts an unidentified group of men and women seated on a train flatbed.
- Biographical and genealogical materials, 1895-2016; Series III
  This series comprises biographical and genealogical materials on the Allen family. The majority of the series was created by Walter Hinds Allen, with exception of a compilation of obituaries about and tributes to his father, Walter Allen. Biographical materials include Allen's school notes, journal entries and the obituaries. Genealogical materials consist of several genealogical charts of different branches of the family and research notes.
  Series III is arranged alphabetically.
  - Biographical materials
    - Compiled obituaries of Walter Allen, 1907, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Journal entries, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Student notebook, Circa 1895-circa 1896 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Genealogical materials
    - General, 1906-1928 (Box 3, Folder 4, Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Allen, Walter Hinds, 2014-2016 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Stark-Harrison and Stark-Mitchell genealogical charts and related notes, Circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Stark, Mitchell, and Hancock family information, 1869-1892, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)